A Guide to the Papers of Thomas Taylor Hammond 1949-1992
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II Articles, lecture notes, and papers
  - Khrushchev-Articles 1965-1971 (Box-folder 13:3)
  - Khrushchev Lifestyle-Articles 1954-1971 (Box-folder 13:4)
  - Khrushchev Economic Reform-Articles 1958-1965 (Box-folder 13:5)
  - Khrushchev Economic Reform-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 13:6)
  - Khrushchev's Successor-Articles 1964-1966 (Box-folder 13:7)
  - Khrushchev's Successor-Lecture notes [1963-1965] (Box-folder 13:8)
  - Krushschev and Tito-Articles 1957-1958 (Box-folder 13:9)
  - Khrushchev and Tito-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 13:10)
  - Kremlin-Article 1960 (Box-folder 13:11)
  - Labor-Articles 1955-1971 (Box-folder 13:12)
  - Labor-Lecture notes 1963-1968 (Box-folder 13:13)
  - Laos-Articles 1959-1964 (Box-folder 13:14)
  - Latin America-Articles n.d. (Box-folder 14:1)
  - Latin America-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 14:2)
  - Law-Articles 1957-1964 (Box-folder 14:3)
  - Laws, Courts-Articles and two papers 1959-1980 (Box-folder 14:4)
    papers- Controlling Dissent in the Soviet Union, David E. Powell, Jan. 1970; The Practice and Status of Intervention and Non-Intervention in Contemporary International Law, Larman C. Wilson
  - Laws, Courts-Lecture notes 1964-1984 (Box-folder 14:5)
  - Lenin-Lecture notes 1978-1986 (Box-folder 14:6)
  - Liberals-Article 1957 (Box-folder 14:7)
  - Literature-Articles 1953-1979 (Box-folder 14:8)
  - Literature-Lecture notes 1958-1978 (Box-folder 14:9)
  - Litvinov-Article 1953 (Box-folder 14:10)
  - Litvinov-Lecture notes 1963 (Box-folder 14:11)
  - Living Standards-Articles 1960-1989
  - Living Standards-Lecture notes 1964-1975 (Box-folder 14:13)
  - Loyalty-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 14:14)
  - Malenkov-Articles 1954-1957 (Box-folder 14:15)
  - Russia Under Malenkov (Thesis) 1958 summer (Box-folder 14:16)
  - Malenkov-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 14:17)
  - Management-Articles 1958-1980 (Box-folder 14:18)
  - Management Lecture notes 1978-1984 (Box-folder 14:19)
  - Marxism and Leninism: Articles and a paper 1949-1962 (Box-folder 14:20)
    paper: The Concept of Imperialism in Leninist Thought, Alfred G. Meyer, The Russian Research Center, Harvard
  - Marxiism-leninism-Lecture notes [1971-1986] (Box-folder 14:21)
  - Medecine-Articles 1952-1967 (Box-folder 15:1)
  - Middle East-Article 1974 (Box-folder 15:2)
  - Middle East-Lecture notes 1974-1977 (Box-folder 15:3)
  - Military-Articles 1964-1967; 1982-1983 (Box-folder 15:4)
  - Military-Lecture notes 1982 (Box-folder 15:5)
  - Minorities-Article 1951-1962 (Box-folder 15:6)
  - Molotov-Article 1954 (Box-folder 15:7)
  - Mongolia-Article 1959-1974 (Box-folder 15:8)
  - Mongolia-Lecture notes 1959-1999 (Box-folder 15:9)
  - Munich-Articles and a paper 1958-1989 (Box-folder 15:10)
    paper: Moscow and Munich 1938, Albert Resis, November 3, 1984
  - Munich-Lecture notes [1973-1986] (Box-folder 15:11)
  - National Character of Russia-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 15:12)
  - Nationalities-Articles and two papers 1953-1975 (Box-folder 15:13)
    papers-Turkic National Tensions in the USSR, David Nissman, and Ukrainian National Tensions, author unnamed
  - Nazi-Soviet Pact-Articles 1953-1971 (Box-folder 15:14)
  - Nazi-Soviet Pact-Lecture notes [1973-1986] (Box-folder 15:15)
  - Nicaragua-Articles 1985-1987 (Box-folder 15:16)
  - Nicaragua-Lecture notes [1986] (Box-folder 15:17)
  - Nineteen twenty-one as a Turning Point-Lecture notes [1973-1982] (Box-folder 15:18)
  - Party Structure-Articles 1969-1982 (Box-folder 16:1)
  - Party Structure-Lecture notes [1973-1986] (Box-folder 16:2)
  - Party Structure Leadership-poster 1979 (Box-folder 16:3)
  - Past History and Its Influence on Foreign Policy in Russia-Articles 1964 (Box-folder 16:4)
  - Peace-Articles 1956-1974 (Box-folder 16:5)
  - Peace-Lecture notes [1952; 1964] (Box-folder 16:6)
  - Pentagon Papers-Articles 1971 (Box-folder 16:7)
  - Perestroika 1987-1990 (Box-folder 16:8)
  - Peter the Great-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 16:9)
  - Pobedonostsev Official-Conservatives-Articles 1953 (Box-folder 16:10)
  - Poland-Article and a paper 1967 (Box-folder 16:11)
    Paper-Joseph Pilsudski, The Bolshevik Revolution and Eastern Europe, Professor Dziewanowski
  - Poland-Lecture notes [1973-1976] (Box-folder 16:12)
  - Police-Article 1967 (Box-folder 16:13)
  - Police-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 16:14)
  - Polish Riots-Articles 1970-1971 (Box-folder 16:15)
  - Political Revolution-Articles 1967 (Box-folder 16:16)
  - Polycentralism-Articles 1962-1967 (Box-folder 16:17)
  - Popular Front-Article signed by author 1950 (Box-folder 16:18)
  - Popular Front-Lecture notes [1969-1986] (Box-folder 16:19)
  - Propaganda-Articles, a State Report(Intelligence) and a speech 1953-1966 (Box-folder 16:20)
    speech by Andrew Berding to the Charlottesville Council On World Affairs
  - Propaganda-Lecture notes 1961 (Box-folder 16:21)
  - Rebellious Intellectuals and Repression-Articles 1957-1965 (Box-folder 17:1)
  - Rebellious Intellectuals and Repression-Articles 1968-1972 (Box-folder 17:2)
  - Reforms Since 1953-Articles 1955-1963 (Box-folder 17:3)
  - Reforms Since 1953-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 17:4)
  - Religion-Articles 1954-1964 (Box-folder 17:5)
  - Religion-Articles 1965-1974 (Box-folder 17:6)
  - Religion-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 17:7)
  - Re-Stalinization-Articles 1966-1973 (Box-folder 17:8)
  - Rise of Hitler-Articles 1971-1972 (Box-folder 17:9)
  - Rise of Hitler-Lecture notes [1945-1973] (Box-folder 17:10)
  - Role of the Military-Articles 1957-1969 (Box-folder 17:11)
  - Role of the Military-Lecture notes [1970] (Box-folder 17:12)
  - Russia-Internal K Revolution-Articles 1955-1963 (Box-folder 17:13)
  - Russia's Development-Articles n.d. (Box-folder 17:14)
  - Russia's Future-Articles 1963-1983 (Box-folder 17:15)
  - Russia's Future-Lecture notes [1970] (Box-folder 17:16)
  - Russian History-Mcknight Seminar Report 1960 (Box-folder 17:17)
  - Russian History 1590-1680-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 17:18)
  - Samizdat-Articles 1960-1970 (Box-folder 18:1)
  - Samizdat-Articles 1971-1975 (Box-folder 17:2)
  - Science-Articles and two papers 1949-1980 (Box-folder 18:3)
    papers-The Crisis of Soviet Biology, Theodosius Dobzhansky and Fifty Years of soviet Science, [John] Turkevich (Hoover Conference)
  - Science-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 18:4)
  - Sino-Soviet Dispute-Articles and a paper 1957-1963 (Box-folder 18:5)
    paper-Third International Sovietological Conference (Convention of the Association for Asian Studies), Pichon P. Y. Loh
  - Sino-Soviet Dispute-Articles 1964-1975 (Box-folder 18:6)
  - Sino-Soviet Dispute-Lecture notes [1957-1965;1973] (Box-folder 18:7)
  - Slovak Soviet Republic-Articles 1958; n.d. (Box-folder 18:8)
  - Social Change-Articles 1971-1982 (Box-folder 18:9)
  - Social Change-Lecture notes [1952] (Box-folder 18:10)
  - Socialism in One Country-Lecture notes 1973-1986 (Box-folder 18:11)
  - Soviet-American Relations-Articles 1959;1970 (Box-folder 18:12)
  - Soviet-American Relations-Lecture notes 1976-1986 (Box-folder 18:13)
  - Soviet Encyclopedia-Article n.d. (Box-folder 18:14)
  - Soviet Interest in Asia-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 18:15)
  - Soviet Society Models-Articles and a paper 1954-1967 (Box-folder 19:1)
    paper-The Socio-Psychological Transformation of Soviet Society, Lewis S. Feuer (Hoover Conference, 1967)
  - Soviet Society Models-Lecture notes 1971 (Box-folder 19:2)
  - Space Race-Articles 1960-1963 (Box-folder 19:3)
  - Spanish Civil War-Article 1977 (Box-folder 19:4)
  - Spanish Civil War-Lecture notes 1969-1986 (Box-folder 19:5)
  - Stalin's Death-Newsclippings 1953 (Box-folder 19:6)
  - Strengths and weaknesses of Soviet Regime-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 19:7)
  - Struggle for Power-Articles 1949-1957 (Box-folder 19:8)
  - Struggle for Power-Articles 1949-1957 (Box-folder 19:8)
  - Succession-Articles 1980-1985 (Box-folder 19:9)
  - Succession-Lecture notes 1982 (Box-folder 19:10)
  - Sweden: Charles XII-Book review 1982 (Box-folder 19:11)
  - Third World-Articles, a paper and a letter in the newspaper 1988-1991 (Box-folder 19:12)
    paper- Soviet Union Third Dialog, General Seinious III (Atlantic Council), newspaper-Open letter from members of the U.S. Government to Minister Shevardnadze about Angola
  - Thought Control-Articles 1944-1981 (Box-folder 19:13)
  - Thought Control-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 19:14)
  - Tito-Articles and an interview given by President Tito to the United Press 1949-1957 (Box-folder 19:15)
  - Tito-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 19:16)
  - Tkachev-Article 1944 (Box-folder 19:17)
  - Trade Unions-Articles 1958-1978 (Box-folder 19:18)
  - Tsarist Foreign Policy-Lecture notes 1947; n.d. (Box-folder 19:19)
  - Turkey (Soviet Relations)- Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 19:20)
  - Unused Lectures n.d. (Box-folder 20:1)
  - USSR-Articles 1985-1986 (Box-folder 20:2)
  - USSR-Articles 1986-1987 (Box-folder 20:3)
  - USSR and U.S.-Lecture notes 1981; 1983; 1987 (Box-folder 20:4)
  - Vietnam-Articles 1957-1966 (Box-folder 20:5)
  - Vietnam-Articles 1967-1975 (Box-folder 20:6)
  - Vietnam-Newsclippings 1967-1975 (Box-folder 20:7)
  - Vietnam-Lecture notes 1977 (Box-folder 20:8)
  - Vietnam Teach-in-Announcement 1967 (Box-folder 20:9)
  - Vietnam-McCarthy for President 1968 (Box-folder 20:10)
  - Vietnam Peaceful Demonstration-Petition n.d. (Box-folder 20:11)
  - Vishinsky-Article 1954 (Box-folder 20:12)
  - Women and Gorbachev-Articles 1970-1978 (Box-folder 21:1)
  - Women-Articles 1955-1973 (Box-folder 21:2)
  - Women-Articles 1975-1984 (Box-folder 21:3)
  - Women-Lecture notes [1971-1990] (Box-folder 21:4)
  - Youth-Articles 1955-1964 (Box-folder 21:5)
  - Youth-Articles 1968-1984 (Box-folder 21:6)
  - Youth-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 21:7)
  - Yugoslavia-Articles 1952-1953 (Box-folder 21:8)
  - Yugoslavia-Lecture notes n.d. (Box-folder 21:9)
  - Yugoslavia-Foreign Policy (Tito)-Articles 1948-1973 (Box-folder 21:10)
  - Yugoslavia Foreign Policy-Lecture notes [1954-1979]
  - Zhukov-Articles 1955 (Box-folder 21:12)
- Series III Course Hand-Outs and Packets (Reading Material) n.d.
  - Course hand-outs: Hieu 189, Hieu 244 and 583; Hist 487/488; Hist EU 384/584; Hist 385/585; Hist 586 1970-1987 (Box-folder 22:1)
    The hand-outs for Hammond's course Hieu 189 are concerned with topics such as Nicholas II; the Collectivization of Agriculture; Achievements of the First Five-Year Plan; Production and Procurement of Grain; The Great Purges of 1934-1938; Stalin's Death Toll, 1930-1953; The Harvest of Sorrow; Deaths due to Collectivism; Dekulakization and Famine; February Revolution; Lenin: Demagogue or Demi-God?
    The hand-outs for Hieu 244 (Sablinsky) are concerned with Russia from the time of Peter the Great.
    The hand-outs for Hammond's course Hieu 583 deal with these subjects: Possibility of Revolution; Russia in WWII; casualties During WWII; Stalin: Paranoid Monser of Steel-Willed Statesman?; Khrushchev: Great Reformer or Incompetent Bungler?; Post Communist Nationalism; Term Paper Topics; Periodicals on current Developments in the USSR; The Power Pyramid of the CPSU; Major Administrative Divisions of the USSR Based onNationality; Organizational Structure of Communist Party; City Government Judicial System; Administrative Divisions; russia and U.S. Comparison In Economy and Population; Soviet Grain Production; Was the Collapse of Tsarist Regime Inevitable?; Why did the Provisional Government fail?; Why did the Bolsheviks win in Oct 1917?; The Civil War: Why did the Reds Defeat the Whites?; and suggested readings.
    The hand-outs for Hist 487/488 include topics on Communist Revolutions in the Third World; Communist Movements Around the World; Changes in the USSR Under Gorbachev and a booklist.
    The hand-outs for Hist 384/584 are on the Soviet Regime. The hand-outs for Hist 385/585 are on the subjects of Allied Intervention in Russia; American Recognition of Russia; and the Nazi Soviet Pact.
    The hand-outs for Hist 586 deal with the origins of the Cold War.
  - Course Packet: Russia From Peter the Great; Sablinsky Hieu 244 1986 (Box-folder 22:2)
    "History of Russia of the Imperial Period: From Peter the Great to the October Revolution", Sablinksy
  - Course Packet 2: Hieu 244 Sablinsky 1987 (Box-folder 22:3)
    Readings include: "The Russian People", Olearius (The Travels of Olearius in the Seventeenth Century Russia); "His Majesty Piter Kneeb Kondor", Boris Pilniak; "Anchar", Alexander Pushkin; "The Sentry", Nikolai Leskov; "Khor and kalynich", ivan Turgenev (Sportsman's Sketches); "The Catechism of the Revolutionary", M. Bakunin and S. Nechaev; "The Threshold", Ivan Turgenev; "Peasants", Anton Chekhov; Petition of workers to be presented to the Tsar on January 9, 1905
  - Course Packet: Russian Since 1917 Hieu 383/583 Hammond 1989 (Box-folder 22:4)
    The course packet includes these articles: "The Populist's Moral Condemnation of Russia's Political & Social systems, Sir Isaiah Berlin; "Causes of Bolshevik Victory", Seton Watson, (Lenin to Khrushchev);"The Revolution in Retrospect", William H. Chamberlin, (The Russian Revolution; "Modernization Was Making Revolution More Remote", Michael Karpovich; "The Approaching Revolutionary Crisis", Boris N. Ponomarev; "The Liberals After 1905",Michael Karpovich; "The Agrarian Situation Was Improving", Lazar Volin; "Industrial Progress Was Improving the Economic System",Alexander Gershenkron; "Nicholas II Was a Bulwark Against Reform", Donald W. Treadgold; "The Philosphic Theory of Marxism", Hunt (The Theory and Practice of Communism); "The Marxist Theory of the State and of the Revolution", Hunt; "Lenin's Contribution to Marxist Theory", Hunt; "Stalin's Contribution to Marxist-Leninist Theory", Hunt; "Impressive Progress Since 1905", S.S. Oldenburg; "Trotsky: The History of the Russian Revolution"; "Descent to Bolshevism", Victor Chernov (The Great Russian Revolution); "Was Lenin a German Agent", A.A.B. Zeman,reviewed by Carsten (Problems of Communism).
  - Course Packet: Russia Since 1917 Hieu 383/583 Hammond 1989 (Box-folder 22:5)
    The course packet includes: " The Allies in Siberia", Kennan (Russia and the West Under Lenin and Stalin; "Disaster", Dispatch from Peter Wrangel to Denikin (Memorirs of General Wrangel); "White Attack", Schuman (War of the Revolution); "Post-Mortem-Brinkley", (The Volunteer's Army); "What the World Owes Khrushchev", Harrison E. Salisbury; "Khrushchevism in Retrospect", Merle Fainsod (Essay in Marxism and the Modern World); "Why Khrushchev Fell" (Peking Review nos. 21-22 Nov. 21, 1964); "The Outster of Khrushchev and Its Consequences", Hammond; "Succession and Institutions in the Soviet Union", Gyorgy (Issues of World Communism); "The Kremlin and the Third World", Philip E. Mosely (The Russian Revolution Fifty Years After); "The Rate of Industrial Growth in Russia); "Soviet Myths and Realities", Philip El. Mosely (Foreign Affairs, Apr. 1961 v.39 no.3); "The Significance of Munich, The Myth",Keith Eubank (Munich: Blunder, Plot, Or Tragic Necessity?); "The Munich Conspiracy", Andrew Rothstein (Munich:Blunder, Plot Or Tragic Necessity?); "Theories of Soviet Foreign Policy", Willaim A. Glaser (World Affairs Quarterly); "The Institute for Policy Studies, A Case History of a Revisionist Think Tank", Rael Jean Isaac; "Lenin Authoritarianism Before the Revolution", Thomas Hammond.
  - Course Packet 2 Hieu 384/584 1984 (Box-folder 22:6)
    Readings include: "Revisionism and the Interpretation of Cold War Origins", Maier (Perspectives in American History); "Revisionism and the Liberal Historians", Maddox (Freedom at Issue); "Cold War Origins", Paul Seabury (Contemporary History); "Budapest and the Hungarian Revolutions of 1918-1919", Istran Deak (The Slavonik Review); "Some Implications of Changes in Soviet Policy toward the West 1949-1952", Marshall D. Shulman (Slavic Review); "Dissent in the Soviet Union", Peter Reddaway (Problems of Communism); "The Social Christian Union for the Liberation of the People", John Danlop (The New Russian Revolutionaries); "The Rise of Dissent in the USSR", Abraham Brumberg (Commentaries); "Introduction", Peter Reddaway (Uncensored Russia); "Russian Imperialism or Communist Aggression?", Michael Karpovich; "Continuity in Russian Foreign Policy", R.S. Tarn; "American Intervention: A Deluded Effort", Christopher Lasch (American Intervention in Siberia); "Chernenko Succeeds", Marc D. Zlotnik (Problems of Communism);"The Man and the System", Jerry F. Hough (The Brezhnev Era) "The Brezhnev To Intervene or Not To Intervene", Hans J. Morgenthau (A New Foreign Policy for the U.S.); "Patterns of Intervention, Richard J. Barnet (Intervention and Revolution); "Gorbachev and the Third World", Francis Fukuyama (Foreign Affairs); "Khrushchev on Modern Art", Nagee (Social Tensions, The World of the Intellectual); "Russian Writers and the Secret Police", Anatoly Kuznetsov; "Youth Soviet Style" (Problems of Communism May -June 1984 p.61-64); "The Emergence of Democracy in Post-Stalinist Russia", William M. Mandel (Popular Participation in the Political Process); "Five years After Krushchev. Tibor Sazmauely; "Alcoholism" (Abstract Sovetskoye Gosudarstvo i Pravo round table discussion, Dec. 1980 no. 12)
  - Course Packet 1: Hist 384/584 Hammond n.d. (Box-folder 23:1)
    Readings include: "The Soviet Family in Post-Stalin Perspective", Peter H. Juviler; "Moscow and the Soviet Jews", Zvi Gitelman (Problems of Communism Jan.-Feb. 1980); "The Soviet Economy On a Treadmill of Reforms", Gertrude Schroeder; "Believers and Non-believers", Bohdan R. Bociurkiw (Equality and Discrimination in Soviet Society); "The Role of Personal Auxiliary Farming", Abstract by G. Dyachkov; Several abstracts from Literaturnaya Gazeta; "Young Mothers Needed in Job Force", I. Bagrova (CDSP XXIX Aug. 1977; "The Soviet Consumer's Woes, A Gift of Mustard", A.I. Struyev (vol. XXX CDSP no. 34); "Appliances in my apartment", Yu Bashkatov CDSP XXI Sept.-Oct. 1978); "Newspaper Takes Trade Minister to Task, Cites Further Abuses" (Knights of the 'Jeans Culture', Lev Kuklin (1979 CDSP XXXII); "My Testimony Soviet Prison Camps Today", Anatoly Marchenko; "Elections, Dissent, and Political Legitimacy", Jerome M. Gilisonm (The Soviet Political System); "The Communist Party", from Brezhnev's report to the 26th Congrss); "Administrative- Territorieal Divisions, The Political Framework" (Geography of the USSR); "Into the Breach: New Soviet Alliances in the Third World", Donald S. Zagoria (Foreign Affairs Spring 1979); "The Secret War in Central America and the the Future of World Order", John Norton Moore (The American Journal of International Law).
  - Course Packet Hist 384/584/586 1984 Fall (Box-folder 23:2)
    The readings include: "Russia Without Stalin, Frankland (Khruschev Ch.10 ); "America", Frankland (Khrushchev Ch. 16); "The Three Months Peace" (Victory and the Seeds of the Cold War); "The Economic Effort of 1942-1943 (Year of Hard Victories, the Polish Tangle); "Soviet Unpreparedness in June 1941" ,Werth ( From the Invasion to the Battle of Moscow); " A Debate on Collectivization Was Stalin really necessary? Miller and Nove (Problems of Communism Jul-Aug 1976); "Kulaki and Individual Peasants, Jasny (Early Kolkhozy and the Big Drive); "The Decision To Collectivize Agriculture", Herbert J. Ellison (The American Slavic and East European Review April 1961); "Stalin on Economic Development", Alexander Erlich; "Soviet Power in Latin America: Success or Failure? W. Raymond Duncan; "Determing Factors in the National-Liberation Movement of Latin America, S.S. Mikhailov
  - Course Packet Nationality Crisis in the Soviet Union Hist 488 Hammond/Gilmore 1991 Spring (Box-folder 23:3)
    Reading material includes: Ethnic Politics in the USSR, Paul Goble (Problems of Communism July-Aug .1989); "Look Who's Feeling Picked On (Time 9/25/89); "Soviet Troops Take Vilnius Buildings (Washington Post 1/12/91); "Baltic Plebiscites Reassert Challenge to Kremlin Leadership (Washington Post 3/5/92); "Ethnic Fighting Kills 3 in Soviet Georgia Region (Washington Post 12/13/90); "The Trouble in Georgia, Rowlan Evans and Robert Novak (Washington Post 12/13/90); "Ethnic Strife Continues in Soviet Area, Washington Post 7/19/89); "On the Edge of Civil War", Paul Hofheinz (Time 10/23/89); "Russia vs. the Soviet Union (U.S. News and World Report 11/5/90); "Moldavia: Potpourri of Political Problems", (U.S. News and World Report 11/5/90); "The Ukraine: Pride in a distinct society" (U.S. News and World Report); "Central Asia: The Rise of the Moslems" (U.S. News and World Report); "The Draft Union Treaty: A Preliminary Assessment", Ann Sheehy (Radio Liberty); "Soviet Union Or Disunion, A Nation's Fate", David Remnick (Washington Post); "Gorbachev Fights to Keep Empire Empire Intact" (Washington Post 12/31/90); "Specter of Soviet Civil War" (Washington Post 10/25/90)
  - Course Packet Hist 488K Hammond 1985 Spring (Box-folder 23:4)
    Reading material includes: "Grenada Is at Ground Zero in Washington's Great Snubbing War", Jackson Diehl (Washington Post 11/21/81); "A Crisis in the Caribbean" (Newsweek 10/31/83); "Leninism in Grenada", Jiri and Virginia Valenta (Problems in Communism July-Aug. 1984 XXXIII); "Grenada" (U.S. Air Force Curren News Special Edition 12/9/83); "Transcript of Shultz News Conference on Invasion of Grenada", (New York Times 10/26/83); "Experts Question Legality of the Invasion of Grenada", (New York Times 10/26/83); Report on the Embassy of Grenada in the USSR.
  - Course Packet Communist Revolution in the Third World Hist 488R Hammond n.d. (Box-folder 23:5)
    Reading material includes: "Revolt in the Congo, 1960-1964", Howard M. Epstein; "U.S. Objectives in the Congo, 1960-65", G. Mennen Williams (Footnotes to the Congo Story August 1965); "Soviet Activities in the Congo" (Bureau of Intelligence and Research Intelligence Report, 8/31/60); "Will the Congo Be Another Vietnam? (U.S. News & World Report 12/21/64); "Four African Views of the Congo Crisis" (Africa Report v.6-7 June 1961-1962); "Implications of Foreign Intervention" (Bureau of Intelligence and Research Intelligence Report Jan. 1961); "Assassination Planning and the Plots" (An Interim Report of the Select Committee to Study Government Operations 94th Congress, First Session); "Soviet Policy in the Developing Countries", Philip E. Mosely (Foreign Affairs 1964-1965).
  - First Year Seminar Course The Russian Revolution: hand-outs with advice for students,and teachers; lecture notes 1978-1983 (Box-folder 23:6)
  - Miscellaneous articles n.d. (Box-folder 23:7)
  - Outline notes of Professor Woodford "Woody" McClellan n.d. (Box-folder 23:8)
- Series IV Exams 1950-1988
  - Exam questions 1950-1988 (Box-folder 24:1)
- Series V Papers written by scholars for conferences
  - Conference:Academic Committee on Soviet Jewry; Paper: Soviet Anti-Semitism, Moshe Dector 1968 October (Box-folder 25:1)
  - Academy of Sciences Discussion (notes) n.d. (Box-folder 25:2)
  - Conference: Air Force Intelligence Conference on Soviet Affairs; Paper: Studying Soviet Low-Intensity Conflicts, Stephen Blank 1988 October 19-22 (Box-folder 25:3)
  - Conference: Annual meeting of the American Political Science Association; Paper: National-International Linkages: The Communist Polities of Eastern Europe, R. V. Burks 1966 September 6-10 (Box-folder 25:4)
  - Arden House Conferences n.d. (Box-folder 25:5)
  - Conference on the Dominant Powers and Subordinate States; Paper: The United States in latin America and the USSR in Eastern Europe, Stanford University; Paper: Historical Overview and Comparative Analysis of the Two Regions, Robert Wesson 1986 January 30-31 (Box-folder 25:6)
  - Hoover Conference: "Fifty Years of Communism" 1967 October (Box-folder 25:7)